1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration Collection
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
- 1. Postcards, 1901-1909; 1.0 linear feet 1 Box (Box 1)
  - Fulton Portrait with Model Clermont Postcard #3, Staining on back from indentations from front image. Various small stains along back top edge. Slight fraying of corners on back. (Box 1)
  - Color Koehler Half-Moon Discovery Postcard #2, Fraying of edges and corners. (Box 1)
  - Manhattan Series: Hudson Monument and Bridge Postcard #6, Faint staining along front bottom and right edge. Small stain on back center left. Fraying of top right and bottom left corner. (Box 1)
  - Hendrik Hudson Dutch Portrait Postcard #2, Faint foxing across front and back. Fraying of edges and corners. Small scratches on bottom left of portrait. (Box 1)
  - Color Hudson-Fulton Celebration Naval Parade Postcard #3, Faint foxing across front and back. Fraying of edges and corners. Small scratches on bottom left of portrait. (Box 1)
  - Manhattan Series: Hudson Portrait Postcard #6, Slight fraying of corners and edges. Large crease across bottom. Various small stains along top to center left edge of image. Faint staining across the back. (Box 1)
  - Manhattan Series: Half-Moon Replica Postcard #6, Fraying of corners and edges. Small stain on back upper right corner. (Box 1)
  - Manhattan Series: Fulton at Clermont Manor Postcard #6, Fraying of corners and edges. Slight discoloration in bottom right corner potentially from previous storage. (Box 1)
  - Manhattan Series: Fulton’s Clermont Sketch Postcard #6, Fraying of corners and edges. Small stain on upper left of image. (Box 1)
  - Manhattan Series: Jonathan Hulls’ Steamboat Postcard #6, Fraying of corners and edges. Small creases in bottom right corner. Large stain on back bottom left center. Stain on back left edge and small stain on upper left. (Box 1)
  - Phenix Insurance Hudson-Fulton Card, Paper is cracked along crease. Slight fraying of edges and corners. Very small stain along bottom right edge. Small indentation on bottom right of front and bottom left of back. (Box 1)
    A card for Hudson-Fulton Celebration, depicting portraits of Hudson and Fulton on front and interior explanations about each man. Back of card is an advertisement for the Phenix Insurance Company based out of Brooklyn, NY.
  - HF Gilded Fold-Out Statue of Liberty Postcard, Fragile along folds. Small stains along top center of back. Two larger stains along bottom center edge of back. Faint staining across back. Fraying of edges. Circular impression in center of card. Gold has worn away along upper right edge of image of “Half-Moon”. Two small holes in top edge of portrait of Hudson. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Fold-out postcard featuring portrait of Hudson and Fulton along with “Half-Moon,” “Clermont,” and the Statue of Liberty. Outline of images and background of Statue of Liberty all gilded with metallic gold. Back of card labels it a “Hudson-Fulton-Souvenir/ from/ Walcutt Bros. Company/ 409 Pearl St., New York.”
  - Hudson-Fulton Celebration Schedule of Events Postcard, Paper is brittle. Along center fold is very fragile. Various, small creases around center fold. Very small tears at either side of fold. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Tri-fold pamphlet featuring black and white image of New York City below headline reading “Hudson-Fulton Celebration”. Inside features explanation of the schedule for the various events associated with the Hudson-Fulton celebration from September 25 to October 9, 1909. Front also includes advertisement for Regal Shoe Stores, as well as information on Hudson and Fulton’s journeys. Copyright 1909, Merrill J. Battel, Publisher.
  - New York 1609-1909 Postcard, Small, circular stains on bottom, center and right, center of card from color transfer from outline of Hudson and Fulton portraits. Center fold is very fragile. Faint staining along outer edge of fold. Small tear in center of fold. Fraying of corners and edges. Very bottom of center fold has begun to deteriorate. Faint staining across left side of back. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Foldout postcard featuring images of New York City and the Hudson Valley in 1609 compared to 1909, including the Hudson Highlands, Anthony’s Nose, Sugar Loaf Mountain, Fort Putnam, the Statue of Liberty, the Brooklyn Bridge, the Williamsburg Bridge, and the Singer Building. Card also features portraits of Hudson and Fulton beside images.
  - Newburgh, NY Hudson-Fulton Postcard, Light foxing across front top center to left of image and across back. Fraying of corners and edges. Stain on center back. Warping of paper along top edge. Small scratches in upper right corner of image. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Depicts black and white photo of Newburgh, NY during Hudson-Fulton Celebration from view on the Hudson River on October 1, 1909. Bottom right label reads “Chappell—Owego, NY”.
  - U.S. Salem Newburgh, NY Postcard, Faint foxing across front and back. Faint staining across top of image and on back left. Fraying of corners and edges. Various faint scratches in upper right of image. Various small stains on bottom right of image. Warping of paper along top edge. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Depicts black and white photo of the “U.S. Salem” sailing along the Hudson River for the Hudson Fulton Celebration on October 1, 1909. Bottom right label reads “Chappell—Owego, NY”.
  - Ferries on Hudson Newburgh, NY Postcard, Very faint foxing across front and back. Faint staining across top of image. Various faint scratches across top image—predominant in upper right corner. Fraying of corners and edges. Warping of paper along top edge. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Depicts black and white photo of ferries on Hudson River in Newburgh, NY for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration on October 1, 1909. Bottom right label reads “Chappell—Owego, NY”.
  - Cruiser on Hudson Newburgh, NY Postcard, Faint foxing across front but more pronounced on back. Faint staining across top of image and back. Various small stains on top left of image. Small stains on top right corner of image. Fraying of corners and edges. Warping of paper along top edge. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Depicts black and white photo of cruiser on Hudson River in Newburgh, NY for Hudson-Fulton Celebration on October 1, 1909. Bottom right label reads “Chappell—Owego, NY”.
  - German SMS Victoria Louise Newburgh, NY Postcard, Very faint foxing across front but more pronounced on back. Various small stains on top left of image. Large stain on upper right corner and left, center of image. Center left stain has bled through from the back. Faint staining across rest of back. Slight fraying of corners and edges. Warping of paper along top edge. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Depicts black and white photo of the German “SMS Victoria Louise” on Hudson River in Newburgh, NY for Hudson-Fulton Celebration on October 1, 1909. Bottom right label reads “Chappell—Owego, NY”.
  - Half-Moon Replica Newburgh, NY Postcard, Very faint foxing across front and back. Faint staining across back. Fraying of corners and edges. Faint staining across top of image. Various small stains on upper right corner and along right edge of image. Various stains along left edge of image. Large outline stain on bottom left of image. Small stains along top edge of image. Two large, faint stains on top left of image. Small stain on top center of image. Small crease on bottom, center right of image. Warping of paper along top edge. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Depicts black and white photo of the replica “Half-Moon” on Hudson River in Newburgh, NY for Hudson-Fulton Celebration on October 1, 1909. Bottom right label reads “Chappell—Owego, NY”.
  - Central Railroad of New Jersey Ship Newburgh, Faint foxing and very faint staining across back. Faint staining along edges of image. Various small stains on top right of image. Fraying of corners and edges. Warping of paper along top edge. Various faint, small scratches along upper right edge of image. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Depicts black and white photo of “Central Railroad of New Jersey” ship on Hudson River in Newburgh, NY for Hudson-Fulton Celebration on October 1, 1909. Bottom right label reads “Chappell—Owego, NY”.
- 2. Photographs, 1909-1915; 0.47 linear feet 1 Box (Box 2)
  Photographs of and involving The 1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
  - Celebration Ship on Hudson Photo (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white photo of one of the celebration ships for Hudson-Fulton on the Hudson River.
  - Steel Hull Ship Photo (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white photo of ship on Hudson River. Bottom has handwritten label “Note—Steel Hull”.
  - Celebration Ship and Factories Photo (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white close-up photo of Hudson-Fulton Celebration ship with background of factories along Hudson River bank.
  - U.S.S. Cuttlefish Photo (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white photo of U.S.S. Cuttlefish on Hudson River during Hudson-Fulton Celebration in New York City in 1909.
  - U.S.S. Connecticut with 46 Star Flag Photo (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white photo of Hudson-Fulton Celebration ship flying a 46-star flag. Handwritten note on back labels the ship “U.S.S. Connecticut”.
  - U.S.S. Idaho Photo (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white photo of Hudson-Fulton Celebration ship on Hudson River during New York City Hudson-Fulton Celebration in 1909. Handwritten note on back labels the ship “U.S.S. Idaho”.
  - U.S.S. Montana Photo (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white photo of celebration ship on Hudson River during Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Handwritten note on back labels the ship “U.S.S. Montana”.
  - New Jersey Class Ship Photo (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white photo of ships on Hudson River during Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Handwritten note on back labels ship “New Jersey Class”.
  - HMS Argyll Photo (Box 2)
  - HMS Argyll Photo #2 (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white photo of British ship “HMS Argyll” on the Hudson River for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Handwritten note on back labels ship “HMS Argyle”.
  - Duke of Edinburgh Photo, Black fleck of unknow substance on right center of image. (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white photo of British ship “Duke of Edinburgh” on Hudson River for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Handwritten note on back labels ship “Duke of Edinburgh”.
  - HMS Drake Photo (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white photo of British ship “HMS Drake” on Hudson River for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Handwritten note on back labels ship “HMS Drake”.
  - French Verite Photo (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white photo of French ship “Verite” on Hudson River for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Handwritten note on back labels ship “Verite”.
  - Audience on the Hudson Photo, Small crease in upper right of image and upper right corner. Small scratch over middle to center right of image. (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white photo of audience of people posing for photo while observing Hudson-Fulton Celebration on Hudson River 1909.
  - Celebration Ships on Hudson Photo, Small scratches throughout image. Small crease in upper right of image. Very small crease in upper left corner. (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white photo of various ships on Hudson River for Hudson-Fulton Celebration in 1909.
  - Cruiser on the Hudson Photo, Small scratches along bottom edge of image. Several scratches of various sizes in bottom left of image. Two creases in left center of image. Creasing in bottom left of image. (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white photo of cruiser on Hudson River for Hudson-Fulton Celebration 1909.
  - Various Cruisers on Hudson Photo, Small scratches throughout image. Creases in upper left, upper right, and bottom left corners. Crease in center left of image. (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white photo of cruisers on Hudson River for Hudson-Fulton Celebration 1909.
  - British Duke of Edinburgh on Hudson Photo, Small scratch on right edge of image. (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white image of British ship “Duke of Edinburgh” on Hudson River for Hudson-Fulton Celebration 1909. Image is slightly blurry.
  - West Point Cadets Parade Photo, Very small crease in upper right corner. (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white photo of West Point Cadets on horseback in Hudson-Fulton Celebration Parade 1909.
  - Settler Parade Float Photo (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white photo of settlers’ float in Hudson-Fulton Celebration Parade 1909.
  - Half-Moon Parade Float Photo, Small crease in left center edge of image. (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white photo of Half-Moon float in Hudson-Fulton Celebration Parade 1909.
  - Mounted Officers Hudson-Fulton Parade Photo (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white photo of mounted officers in Hudson-Fulton Celebration Parade 1909.
  - Cadets Hudson-Fulton Parade Photo, Creasing along top edge and bottom right edge of image. Scratches along bottom of image. (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white photo of cadets marching in Hudson-Fulton Celebration Parade 1909.
  - One-Cylinder Automobile Photo, Groups of small scratches in middle center left and top of image. (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and photo of a couple in a one-cylinder automobile in 1909. Handwritten note labels image “1 cyl. CAD”.
  - E-M-F Everitt 30 Automobile Photo, Small creases and scratches over image. (Box 2)
    Reproduction black and white photo of E-M-F’s “Everitt 30” automobile with background of Iron Founders factory building. Handwritten note labels car “1915 Everett).
  - Start of Hudson-Fulton Celebration Parade Photo (Box 2)
    Black and white photo depicting the start of the Hudson-Fulton Celebration Parade on 110th Street. Stamp on back dates the photo September 28, 1909.
  - Hudson-Fulton Parade Floats Photo, Small creases in upper right corner of image. Slight fraying of corners and edges. Bottom left corner bent. Large creased from top to bottom of right of image. (Box 2)
    Black and white photo depicting two parade floats in Hudson-Fulton Celebration Historical Parade. Stamp on back dates the photo September 28, 1909.
- 3. Souvenirs and Plates, 1909; 1.0 linear feet 1 Box (Box 3)
  Commemorative plates, porcelain, and other souvenirs associated with The 1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
  - Hudson-Fulton Celebration Souvenir Plate, Three large cracks along bottom edges of plate. Each have been previously repaired. Crazing of glaze over entire front and back. Staining along top and along each crack. Small stains along right outside edge. Small chip on back, left center edge. (Box 3)
    Souvenir plate featuring Dutch delft-style blue and white art of the NYS Capitol in Albany, NY, the Poughkeepsie Bridge in Poughkeepsie, NY, Washington’s Headquarters in Newburgh, NY, the Old Senate House in Kingston, NY, Grant’s Tomb in NYC, and Fulton’s “Clermont”. Bottom reads “Souvenir of Hudson-Fulton Tercentenary”. Plate manufactured by Frank Beardmore & Co in Fenton, England for The Geo. H. Bowman Co. based out of Cleveland and New York. Back of plate also stamped with the number “2” beside maker’s mark. Maker’s mark stamped on center of back.
  - Hudson-Fulton Celebration Souvenir Plate #2, Crazing in glaze over entire front and back. Small stains along right outside edge. Small stain on front, upper left edge. Faint stain on front, upper right corner. Small stains around edges. Small chip on back, right center and back, bottom center. Small raised stain on back, upper left corner. (Box 3)
  - Hudson-Fulton Celebration Souvenir Plate #3, Crazing in glaze over entire front and back. Small stains on front, center, top center, right center and left center. Stain on back center. Deep scratch in china under the maker’s mark. Small, faint staining along back, top, left, and bottom edge. Small chips in back, upper right corner, left center edge, and bottom right edge. (Box 3)
  - Landing of Hendrik Hudson Plate, Crazing in glaze has begun along front, bottom right edge and on back left and bottom edges. Small stain on back, center left. Small scratch on back, upper left corner. Small stain on back, upper left outer edge. Various small scratches across edges of front. Small, deep scratch on back, bottom center. (Box 3)
    Plate featuring scalloped edges and Dutch delft-style blue and white art of Henry Hudson’s landing in the “Half-Moon” in the center, with images of Fulton and his “Clermont,” Washington’s Headquarters in Newburgh, NY, Federal Hall on Wall Street where Washington took oath of office, and Fraunces Tavern in NYC along the edges. Produced by Ye Olde Historical Pottery in Staffordshire, England. Its stamped “No. 5” of “Rd. No. 563256” beside maker’s mark. Maker’s mark stamped on center of back.
  - Landing of Hendrik Hudson Plate #2, Crazing in glaze across entire front and back. Two chips along bottom outside edge. Two small, black stains on front, bottom left edge. Chip on back, top center edge. Residual piece of possibly price sticker remains on front, upper right corner. (Box 3)
  - Landing of Hendrik Hudson Plate #3, Crazing in glaze across entire front and back. Various small, faint scratches across entire front. Very small circular stain on front, bottom right edge. Small stain on back, upper right corner. Small chip on back upper left corner. Two small spots of tape residue on back, center to the right and directly above maker’s mark. (Box 3)
  - The “Aero” Plate, Crazing in glaze across entire front and back. Small stain on back, right center edge and on top center. Small chips individually located on back bottom right edge, upper right corner, and left center edge. Various, small faint scratches across front. Very small, circular stain on front, center right. (Box 3)
    Plate featuring Dutch delft-style blue and white art of airplanes and zeppelins flying over the Hudson River and ship sailing on the river for Hudson-Fulton Celebration 1909. Maker’s mark labels the plate “The ‘Aero’ Plate/ Hudson-Fulton Celebration/ September & October/ 1909”. Manufactured by Royal Doulton in England for Higgins & Seiter, New York. Maker’s mark stamped on center of back.
  - The “Aero” Plate #2, Crazing in glaze over entire front and back. Staining along back edges, predominantly along back bottom edge. Small chip located in bottom center edge, and in upper left corner. Two very small chips in back, center right edge Residue of unknown tacky substance on center and center, right of back. Small stain on front, center left. Two small stains located along front, left outer edge. (Box 3)
  - The “Aero” Plate #3, Crazing in glaze over entire front and back. Small chip in back, bottom left corner. Small chip in center, bottom of back. Small chip in back, center left edge. Large stain on back top center to top right edge. Small chip in back, upper right corner. Various small, faint scratches across front. (Box 3)
  - The “Aero” Plate #4, Crazing in glaze over entire front and back. Small, faint stain on back, center left. Residue of unknown tacky substance on back, center top left and top center edge. Small chip in back upper right edge. Small chip in back upper left edge. Various small, faint scratches across front. Small spot of residue from unknown substance on center, right of front. (Box 3)
  - Landing of Hendrick Hudson and Half-Moon Plate, Crazing in glaze across entire front and back. Faint staining along back, center raised edges. Small stain on back, top center edge. Small stain on back, center left and center left edge. Faint staining on front, left center edge. Small stain on front, upper right corner. Various small, faint scratches across front. Several small stains along front, top center edge. Very small, circular stain on front, right center edge. Faint staining along outside edges. (Box 3)
    Deep plate featuring Dutch delft-style blue and white art of Henry Hudson’s landing in the “Half-Moon” in the center, with images of Fulton and his “Clermont,” Washington’s Headquarters in Newburgh, NY, State Capitol Building in Albany, NY, Grant’s Tomb in NYC, the S.S. Hendrick Hudson, and a view of West Point from the North around the edges. Manufactured by The Rowland & Marsellus Co. in Staffordshire, England. Maker’s mark stamped on center of back.
  - Landing of Hendrick Hudson and Half-Moon Plate #2, Crazing in glaze over entire front and back. Faint staining around outside edges. Small stain on back, left center edge. Faint stain on back, top left. Small, faint scratches on back top right edge. Discoloration along front bottom and top edge. Small brown stain on front, bottom center edge. Very small stains on center right of front. Various small, faint scratches across front. (Box 3)
  - Landing of Hendrick Hudson and Half-Moon Plate #3, Crazing in glaze across entire front and back. Faint staining along back, left center raised edges. Very small, circular stain on back, bottom center. Price sticker remains on front, upper right corner. Residue of unknow tacky substance, possibly an additional price sticker, remains on front, bottom right corner. Various small, faint scratches across front. (Box 3)
  - Fulton & Clermont Pocket Knife, Tarnished along edges and blades. Small chip on the upper left of Fulton portrait. (Box 3)
    Silver pocket knife with engraved portraits of Hudson and Fulton beside image of “Clermont” below which reads “Robert Fultons Clermont. Reverse side showcases image of modern steamship above date “1909”.
  - Fulton & Clermont Pocket Knife #2, Tarnished along edges and blades. Slight rust visible along edges. Engraved image is worn. Outer case missing most of top layer and slight fraying along front. Small piece of top layers missing beside button clasp. (Box 3)
  - Hudson-Fulton Dutchess County Society Soap Dish, Some of the gilding along edges has worn away. Staining across raised portion of back. Small, black stain on back, right edge. Unknown residue over first maker’s mark. (Box 3)
    Gilded, scalloped edge porcelain soap dish featuring color image of Dutch flag medal featuring the Dutchess County Society crest. Below crest reads “The Dutchess County Soc’y”. First maker’s mark on back is mostly illegible; what is decipherable reads “…C. Rich/ New York”. Second mark indicates dish was produced in Limoges, France.
  - Hotel Manhattan Hudson-Fulton Cup and Saucer, Faint staining along raised edge of back center. Small stain along top of center, above maker’s marks. Cup has forked crack on “Hudson-Fulton” side from top to middle of side. Small stain on bottom center. (Box 3)
    Small, white cup and saucer with blue outer edge and orange edge around bottom of cup/handle and center of saucer. Sides of cup and top and bottom of saucer read “Hotel Manhattan/ New York” and “Hudson-Fulton/ 1609-1807”. Cup features Dutch and American flag together. First maker’s mark establishes that dish was produce in Limoges, France by Theodore Haviland. Second mark establishes dish was produced for James M. Shaw & Co. in New York in 1909. Dish also labelled number “9” potentially in a series.
  - Half-Moon Napkin Ring, Tarnish over entire ring. Edges still remain original golden color. Small speckles across back of ring where plated metal is visible through silver. (Box 3)
    Silver-plated napkin ring featuring engraved image of Hudson’s “Half-Moon” below banner for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Maker’s mark for K & Co. labels item “Quadruple Plate” indicting the amount of plating on the item to be 0.0012 inches.
  - Clermont Napkin Ring, Tarnish over entire ring. However, some silver remains bright along bottom of image and inside ring. Small speckles across back of ring where plated metal is visible through silver. (Box 3)
    Silver-plated napkin ring featuring engraved image of Fulton’s “Clermont” beneath banner for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Maker’s mark for K & Co. labels item “Quadruple Plate” indicting the amount of plating on the item to be 0.0012 inches.